[
  {
    "question": "A 25 years old male presented with complaints of right ear pain and decreased hearing from the last 2 days. According to the patient, his symptoms started after coming back from swimming in a local pond. O/E external auditory canal appears red and congested. Organism responsible for this condition is:",
    "options": [
      "Ecoli",
      "hemophilus influenza",
      "mozarella catarrhalis",
      "streptococcus pneumoniae",
      "Yersinia pestis"
    ],
    "answer": "Yersinia pestis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old female was involved in a road traffic accident. She received trauma to the left temporal bone. When she was examined, she had intact hearing but had decreased lacrimation left eye. The nerve involved is.",
    "options": [
      "chorda tympani nerve",
      "facial nerve branch to posterior belly of digastric",
      "greater superficial petrosal nerve",
      "nerve to stapedius:",
      "tympanic plexus"
    ],
    "answer": "greater superficial petrosal nerve"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 23 year old patient comes to Ophthalmology outpatient department with complaints of redness and pain in his right eye. The pain is dull, continuous and associated with decreased vision. On examination, he has circumeiliary redness, mild corneal edema, and +3 cells and flare in the anterior chamber. The rest of eye examination is unremarkable. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Allergic Conjunctivitis",
      "Nodular Scleritis",
      "Bacterial conjunctivitis",
      "Anterior Uveitis",
      "Acute congestive glaucoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Anterior Uveitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 years old diabetic female presented with complaints of severe pain right ear, fever and serous discharge from right ear from the last 2 weeks. She is on oral hypoglycemics. Her blood investigations reveal poor glycemic control with HbA1C of 10%. Examination of right ear reveals a congested external canal with serous discharge and is very tender. This patient is suffering from",
    "options": [
      "Herpes Zoster Oticus",
      "keratosis obturans",
      "malignant otitis externa",
      "otemycosis",
      "osteoma"
    ],
    "answer": "malignant otitis externa"
  },
  {
    "question": "A newborn is noticed to have bilateral leukocoria by a Paediatrician and is referred to the eye clinic. On eye examination the neonate is found to have oil droplet lens opacities in both eyes. Which systemic condition is associated with this type of congenital cataract?",
    "options": [
      "Lowe syndrome",
      "Galactosemia",
      "Down syndrome",
      "Edwards syndrome",
      "Fabry disease"
    ],
    "answer": "Galactosemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30-year-old female presents with recurrent episodes of severe vertigo associated with hearing loss and tinnitus. Patient suddenly falls on the ground without loss of consciousness. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Vestibular neuritis",
      "Meniere's disease",
      "Benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV)",
      "Acoustic neuroma",
      "Labyrintitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Meniere's disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 4 years old female child presented with complaints of delayed speech and decreased hearing since childhood. O/E both tympanic membranes looked normal. She was investigated and found to have a sensorineural hearing loss of 95db. She was put in the cochlear implant surgery program. Before embarking on surgery, which investigation should be ordered",
    "options": [
      "Brain stem evoked response audiometry",
      "CT scan to rule out inner ear anomalies",
      "Midbrain evoked potentials",
      "MRI to rule out brain pathology",
      "PET scan for viable audiologic pathways"
    ],
    "answer": "CT scan to rule out inner ear anomalies"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2 months old infant is brought to eye OPD by his mother having noticed a white pupil in his left eye. After examination a diagnosis of congenital cataract is made by the Ophthalmologist. Which of the following is the most common type of congenital cataract presenting with visual impairment?",
    "options": [
      "subcapsular cataract",
      "nuclear",
      "polar",
      "lamellar",
      "oil droplet"
    ],
    "answer": "lamellar"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70 years old gentleman who is otherwise fit presents to eye OPD with gradual progressive visual loss for last 2 years. His visual acuity were recorded as 6/24 both eyes and improved to 6/9 with pinhole. He was previously emmetropic but now his refractive error was -2.00 diopter. Pupillary responses and intraocular pressures are normal. On distant direct ophthalmoscopy there is media opacity which does not move with movement of the eye. The most likely diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "Asteroid hyalosis",
      "Corneal opacity",
      "Nuclear sclerosis cataract",
      "Posterior vitreous detachment",
      "Vitreous haemorrhage"
    ],
    "answer": "Nuclear sclerosis cataract"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 15 years old boy with vernal keratoconjunctivitis presents with gradual loss of vision in both of his eyes. He gives history of using topical dexamethasone eyedrops for many years. On examination his visual acuity in the right eye was 6/12 and left was 6/60. Both corneas were clear. His intraocular pressure was 24mmHg in the right and 30mmHg in the left eye. On fundoscopy cup-disc ratio was 0.5 in the right and 0.8 in the left eye. What is the probable diagnosis",
    "options": [
      "Keratoconus",
      "Steroid induced glaucoma",
      "Optic atrophy",
      "Congenital glaucoma",
      "Keratoglobus"
    ],
    "answer": "Steroid induced glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 years old male with involved in a road traffic accident. He presented to ER with a concussion and a fractured nose. He is managed conservatively and is making good progress after being shifted to ward. The next day, the surgeon on call receives a call from the ward that the patient has clear fluid coming out from nose, particularly on bending forward and is unable to sniff it back. The investigation to be done in this case is:",
    "options": [
      "B2 transferrin",
      "CSF analysis",
      "serum aldosterone levels",
      "MRI brain",
      "Urinary catecholamines"
    ],
    "answer": "B2 transferrin"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 14 years old adolescent boy presented with complaints of brisk epistaxis from the last 6 months. According to him, the bleeding is so severe that he required a blood transfusion on one instance. O/E, patient had a polypoidal growth right side nasal cavity. The next step in management of this patient would be",
    "options": [
      "Arrange for nasal endoscopy",
      "Manage conservatively",
      "Order a CT scan",
      "Request coagulation profile",
      "Shift for surgery"
    ],
    "answer": "Order a CT scan"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70 years old lady has an ulcerated nodular mass on her right medial lower eyelid for the last 4 years. The central ulceration has raised rolled edges with dilated blood vessels over the lateral margins. Preauricular and submandibular lymph nodes are not palpable. The most likely diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "Basal Cell Carcinoma",
      "Kaposi Sarcoma",
      "Merkle Cell Tumor",
      "Sebaceous Gland Carcinoma",
      "Squamous Cell Carcinoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Basal Cell Carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 65 yrs old lady who is a known patient of Glaucoma comes to eye OPD for visual field testing. On examination she has a central visual field of less than 10 degrees. In which category of visual impairment does she fit according to WHO classification?",
    "options": [
      "Mild visual impairment",
      "Moderate visual impairment",
      "Normal",
      "Severe visual impairment",
      "Blindness"
    ],
    "answer": "Blindness"
  },
  {
    "question": "A young boy presents with rapid onset of right orbital swelling and pain associated with malaise and fever. On examination right eyeball is proptosed axially. There is periorbital and lid oedema with red warm overlying skin and tenderness. Extraocular movements are restricted and painful. Vision is decreased and there is relative afferent pupillary defect. CT scan brain is normal. The most probable diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "Pre septal orbital cellulitis",
      "Acute dacryocystits",
      "Orbital cellulitis",
      "Cavernous sinus thrombosis",
      "Thyroid eye disease (orbitopathy)"
    ],
    "answer": "Orbital cellulitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 years old diabetic female with active covid infection presented with complaints of left facial swelling and decreased vision left eye from the last 7 days. O/E there is diffuse erythema left side face and extensive black eschar is seen in nose. The patient also has complete ophthalmoplegia left eye and necrotic patch on hard palate. The clinical diagnosis in this case is:",
    "options": [
      "Chronic rhinosinusitis",
      "Inverted papilloma",
      "Mucormycosis",
      "Sarcoidosis",
      "Sinonasal malignancy"
    ],
    "answer": "Mucormycosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Despite aggressive treatment strategies, her polyps recur and her chest infections also are getting worse. Her sweat chloride test was ordered and it was abnormal. The child is suffering from",
    "options": [
      "allergic rhinitis",
      "chronic rhinosinusitis",
      "Cystic fibrosis",
      "Rhinolith",
      "sarcoidosis"
    ],
    "answer": "Cystic fibrosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 43 years old male patient came through OPD with the history of nasal obstruction, headache, post nasal drip associated with decreased sense of smell lethargy and intermittent ear clogging. On examination of the nose there is white glistening soft tissue mass which are insensitive to touch. Which is the most suitable option of the following",
    "options": [
      "Acute rhinosinusitis with nasal polyposis",
      "Allergic rhinosinusitis",
      "Acute invasive fungal rhinosinusitis",
      "Chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyposis",
      "Chronic invasive fungal rhinosinusitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyposis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 55-year-old male smoker presents with hoarseness and a progressively worsening cough. He also complains of difficulty swallowing. Laryngoscopy reveals a lesion involving the right vocal cord with irregular borders and areas of ulceration. What is the most appropriate next step?",
    "options": [
      "Empiric antibiotic therapy",
      "Immediate surgical excision",
      "Chest Xray to evaluate for metastasis",
      "Biopsy of the lesion",
      "High-dose corticosteroid therapy"
    ],
    "answer": "Biopsy of the lesion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 10 year old boy came to ENT OPD with right ear pain and discharge since 4 days. There was a previous episode of a common cold. Examination shows small central perforation. The most effective treatment would be",
    "options": [
      "cortical mastoidectomy",
      "Myringotomy",
      "Starting medical treatment",
      "using lignocaine drops to relieve pain",
      "wait for spontaneous improvement"
    ],
    "answer": "Starting medical treatment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old male presented with complaints of decreased hearing right side and fever. According to the patient, the fever is episodic and mostly comes at night with shivering. O/E there is extensive cholesteatoma in right ear. CT reveals erosion of tegmen plate and right sigmoid sinus thrombosis. The management option for this patient is",
    "options": [
      "Atticotomy",
      "Broad spectrum antibiotics",
      "conservative management",
      "modified radical mastoidectomy",
      "tympanoplasty"
    ],
    "answer": "modified radical mastoidectomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 years old male patient who is known case of uncontrolled diabetes and hypertension admitted in medical ward for fever, progressively increasing headache and has developed left periorbital edema for the last one day. On examination there is black crusting in his left nasal cavity and has restricted eye movements with decreased visual acuity. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Allergic Rhinosinusitis",
      "Acute bacterial rhinosinusitis",
      "Acute meningitis",
      "Mucormycosis"
    ],
    "answer": "Mucormycosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50 years old obese lady is complaining of dimness of vision in both eyes. On examination her vision in the right eye is 6/60 and 6/36 in the left eye. On examination of the fundi, there are retinal microaneurysms, hard exudates, haemorrhages and macular oedema. In addition there are new vessels at the optic disc and in retinal periphery. The lady is suffering from:",
    "options": [
      "Central retinal vein occlusion",
      "Hypertensive retinopathy",
      "Central retinal artery occlusion",
      "Diabetic retinopathy",
      "Toxemia of pregnancy"
    ],
    "answer": "Diabetic retinopathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Nine years old child brought by her mother to Otolaryngology clinic giving history of behavioural changes like watching TV with loud sound and doesn't respond to a slow voice calling him from behind for the last 8-10 months. Her hearing was satisfactory before that. On otoscopy, both the tympanic membranes are retracted, dull looking appearance and there is no tenderness on palpation. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Acute otitis media",
      "Chronic otitis media",
      "Chronic mastoiditis",
      "Otitis media with effusion",
      "otis externa"
    ],
    "answer": "Otitis media with effusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 5 weeks-old child is brought to your clinic with high-pitched noise during inspiration and improves with proning. The child appears distressed, and you observe retractions in the suprasternal notch and between the ribs. What is the most likely condition causing these symptoms?",
    "options": [
      "Croup (viral laryngotracheitis)",
      "Epiglottitis",
      "Laryngomalacia",
      "Foreign body aspiration",
      "Vocal cords nodules"
    ],
    "answer": "Laryngomalacia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A three years female child is brought to eye opd with convergent squint for the last 6 months. Extraocular movements and fundi are normal. Ac/A ratio is normal. Cycloplegic refraction shows hypermetropia of 6 diopters. eyes are straight with glasses. What's your probable diagnosis:",
    "options": [
      "Infantile esotropia",
      "exotropia",
      "paralytic esotropia",
      "paralytic exotropia"
    ],
    "answer": "Infantile esotropia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Mother brings her 4-week-old baby to ophthalmology OPD with symptoms of epiphora and sticky mucoid discharge that accumulates on the eyelid margin and lashes. On examination, the regurgitation test is positive. What is the most likely diagnosis:",
    "options": [
      "Bacterial conjunctivitis",
      "Congenital nasolacrimal duct obstruction",
      "Blephartis",
      "Acute dacryoadentis",
      "Viral Keratis"
    ],
    "answer": "Congenital nasolacrimal duct obstruction"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 10 year old boy came to ENT OPD with complain of right ear sever pain and fever followed by cold and flu. He has no previous such history. On otoscopic examination right tympanic membrane is red, congested with loss of light reflex. The most likely cause would be",
    "options": [
      "otitis externa",
      "Cholesteatoma",
      "acute otitis media",
      "otomycosis",
      "myringitis bullosa"
    ],
    "answer": "acute otitis media"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 3-year young boy is brought by his concerned parents after they noticed white pupillary reflex in his left eye. On examination, you found the cornea and lens are clear. You noticed a whitish mass involving the retina. B-scan ultrasound showed calcification in the mass. You are suspecting a possible intraocular tumor. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Coat's disease",
      "Toxocatiasis",
      "Toxoplasmosis",
      "Congenital Cataract"
    ],
    "answer": "Retinoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2 years old boy is brought to the eye OPD by his parents for concerns of misalignment of the eyes. According to the parents the patient's eyes are deviated inwards. On Hirschberg test, the eyes are convergent and deviation is present all the time and in all position of gaze. What is your most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Esotropia",
      "Exotropia",
      "Hypertropia",
      "Hypotropia",
      "Orthophoria"
    ],
    "answer": "Esotropia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 65 years old male presented with complaints of decreased hearing both ears from the last 5 years. According to the patient, he has worked in a factory for 25 years with moderate levels of noise exposure. he is non diabetic and non hypertensive. Both his tympanic membranes are normal with tuning fork tests showing sensorineural hearing loss. Finding you would expect on audiogram of this patient would be:",
    "options": [
      "Airbone gap",
      "catharts notch",
      "Dip in bone conduction at 4kHz",
      "Low frequency SNHL",
      "Rising type curve on PTA"
    ],
    "answer": "Dip in bone conduction at 4kHz"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 years old gentleman comes to you because he cannot see clearly for distance. His present reading glasses are 5 years old. He is otherwise fit. His visual acuity is 6/5 in both eyes corrected with glasses. His refractive error is -2.0 diopter sphere in both eyes. On examination his pupillary responses are normal. Anterior segment examination is normal with deep anterior chambers. His intraocular pressures were recorded as 28 and 30mmHg in the right and left eye respectively. His central corneal thickness is 515 microns in each eye. On fundoscopy he has got cupping of 0.6 in both eyes with nerve fibre layer haemorrhage along the superior border of the left optic disc. Visual field examination shows arcuate scotoma in both eyes. Most likely diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "Myopic degeneration of the retina",
      "Ocular hypertension",
      "Primary open angle glaucoma",
      "Pseudoexfoliative glaucoma",
      "Primary angle closure glaucoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Primary open angle glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 years old male presented with a depressed nasal dorsum from the last 3 years. According to him, his deformity gradually worsened with time. O/E, there is a septal perforation with crusting and a saddle nose. Upon further enquiry, the patient also had red cell casts in urine and decreased renal function. Blood tests were ordered and his C-ANCA came out to be positive. The patient is suffering from",
    "options": [
      "Buergers disease",
      "sarcoidosis",
      "syphilis",
      "tuberculosis",
      "Wegeners granulomatosis"
    ],
    "answer": "Wegeners granulomatosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 14-year-old boy presents with a history of foul-smelling, scanty, persistent ear discharge from the right ear for the past 6 months, associated with progressive hearing loss. He denies ear pain or fever. On otoscopic examination, there is a marginal perforation in the posterosuperior quadrant of the tympanic membrane with crusts and pearly white flakes visible in the middle ear. The posterior canal wall appears eroded.",
    "options": [
      "Chronic otitis media – mucosal type",
      "otitis externa",
      "Tympanosclerosis",
      "cholesteatoma",
      "otitis media with effusion"
    ],
    "answer": "cholesteatoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 years old male patient came through OPD with the history of otalgia due to which he couldn't sleep last night. He also gives history of ear picking. On examination the pinna is tender. What is the most probable diagnosis",
    "options": [
      "Acute otitis media",
      "Acute mastoiditis",
      "Acute otitis externa",
      "Acute parotitis",
      "Acute Rhinosinusitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Acute otitis externa"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50 years old male was involved in a road traffic accident 2 weeks back. He received trauma to left side of face and temporal bone. He had a concussion and was unconscious for 2 days which he spent in ICU. When he regained consciousness, the attending doctors noted asymmetry of his left side of face. The patient had a left facial palsy and even after 12 days, there was no improvement in his facial function. The test that would best indicate the chances of recovery of facial nerve at 2 weeks would be:",
    "options": [
      "Electromyography",
      "Electroneuronagraphy",
      "Minimal nerve excitability test",
      "Maximal nerve stimulation test",
      "Tympanogram"
    ],
    "answer": "Electroneuronagraphy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 14 yrs old boy, who is a known patient of allergic conjunctivitis, presents to eye OPD complaining of painless, progressive dimness of vision. On examination the boy has progressive myopia and astigmatism. Distant direct ophthalmoscopy shows oil droplet reflex. There is bulging of the lower eyelid when the patient looks down. Retinoscopy shows irregular scissor reflex. Slit lamp exam shows thinning and forward bulging of the central cornea. What is the diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "arcus senile",
      "keratoglobus",
      "band keratopathy",
      "lipid keratopathy",
      "keratoconus"
    ],
    "answer": "keratoconus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70 years old man presents to eye OPD with the complaints of watering from his right eye. On examination the right lower eyelid is everted but the skin is not scarred or shortened. There is chronic conjunctivitis and exposure keratitis. The most likely diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "Cicatricial ectropion",
      "Congenital ectropion",
      "Mechanical ectropion",
      "Paralytic (facial nerve palsy) ectropion.",
      "Senile (involutional) ectropion."
    ],
    "answer": "Senile (involutional) ectropion."
  },
  {
    "question": "What would be the appropriate management of a 5 year old child presenting with right foul smelling ear discharge, fever and otalgia. On examination his right pinna is pushed forward.",
    "options": [
      "Topical Antibiotic drops",
      "Topical steroid drops",
      "Oral antibiotics",
      "IV antibiotics with or without cortical mastoidectomy",
      "Watch and wait"
    ],
    "answer": "IV antibiotics with or without cortical mastoidectomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years farmer came to eye opd with the complaints of redness and a triangular shaped fleshy mass at the medial limbus with the apex towards cornea for the last 1 year. The most probable diagnosis is",
    "options": [
      "pterygium",
      "psudopterygium",
      "pingicula",
      "scleritis",
      "episcleritis"
    ],
    "answer": "pterygium"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 45 years old lady visits Ophthalmology outpatient department with complaints of mild discomfort in her eyes since last 2 months. It is associated with gradual deterioration of vision. On examination, she has intraocular pressure of 28 mm of Hg in both her eyes. The cup to disc ratio in her eyes are 0.8. What is the first line drug used to treat her condition?",
    "options": [
      "Cyclopentolate eye drops",
      "Dexamethasone eye drops",
      "Infusion Mannitol",
      "Prostaglandin analogues",
      "Intravitreal anti-VEGF"
    ],
    "answer": "Prostaglandin analogues"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old male presented with complaints of left side nasal bleeding and pain from the last 6 months. O/E, patient had a fungating growth arising from left maxillary sinus and extending out in the nasal cavity. There were extensive erosions but no cervical lymphadenopathy. The next step in management of this patient would be",
    "options": [
      "Biopsy under local anaesthesia",
      "chemotherapy",
      "nasal endoscopy",
      "surgical resection",
      "wait and watch"
    ],
    "answer": "Biopsy under local anaesthesia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50 years old lady presents to eye O.P.D with the complaint of watering and burning sensation in her Rt. Eye. On examination the patient has Rt. Lagophthalmos and exposure keratitis. Her mouth is deviated to the left side and is unable to lift her Rt. eyebrow. The eyelid skin is normal. The most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Cicatricial ectropion.",
      "Congenital ectropion",
      "Congenital ectropion",
      "Paralytic (facial nerve palsy) ectropion",
      "senile (involutional) ectropion"
    ],
    "answer": "Paralytic (facial nerve palsy) ectropion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 65 years old man has an ulcerated nodular mass on isr right medial lower eyelid for the last 4 years. The central ulceration has raised rolled edges with dilated blood vessels over the lateral margins. Regional lymph nodes are not palpable. The most likely diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Basal Cell Carcinoma",
      "Kaposi sarcoma",
      "Merkle Cell Tumor",
      "Sebaceous Gland Carcinoma",
      "Squamous Cell Carcinoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Basal Cell Carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 09 months old baby is brought to Ophthalmology outpatient department. The parents are complaining of him not following objects and inattention to light. There is no history of prematurity. On examination the patient has white pupillary reflex in both his eyes. Rest of the clinical examination is normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Coats disease",
      "Congenital cataracts",
      "Retinopathy of prematurity",
      "Toxocariasis"
    ],
    "answer": "Congenital cataracts"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old male with uncontrolled diabetes presents with left sided facial pain and swelling from the last 6 days. O/E he had fungal debris occupying left maxillary sinus and left ethmoids. It has breached the left lamina papyracea but has not yet involved the orbit. He is diagnosed as having acute fulminant fungal rhinosinusitis. The key to achieving disease control in this case is:",
    "options": [
      "anti fungals",
      "IV antibiotics",
      "good renal function",
      "hyperbaric Oxygen",
      "strict glucose control"
    ],
    "answer": "strict glucose control"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 4 years old male presented with fever and right ear pain from the last 5 days. According to the patient's mother, he had severe pain in the right ear but his condition improved when she observed yellowish foul smelling discharge in his right ear. Culture of this discharge will likely yield which pathogen",
    "options": [
      "bacteroids fragilis",
      "Clostridium difficile",
      "E.coli",
      "Moxarella Catarrhalis",
      "Streptococcus Pneumoniae"
    ],
    "answer": "Streptococcus Pneumoniae"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2-year-old boy is brought by his concerned parents to ophthalmology OPD for a white pupillary reflex in his right eye. On examination, there is a white pupillary reflex and outward deviation of the eye. B-scan ultrasonography shows an intra-ocular, calcified mass. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Toxocariasis",
      "Coats's disease",
      "Congenital cataracts",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Persistent hyperplastic primary vitreous"
    ],
    "answer": "Retinoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 28 years old female presented to eye OPD with complaints of right eye painful swelling at the medial canthus. There is associated epiphora and redness. on examination there is a swelling near the medial canthus, the overlying skin is red, it is tender to touch and purulent discharged is present. she most likely has",
    "options": [
      "chronic dacryocystitis",
      "presepta cellulitis",
      "acute dacryocystitis",
      "bacterial conjunctivitis",
      "acute dacryoadenitis"
    ],
    "answer": "acute dacryocystitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20 years girl presents to EYE-OPD with a gradual painless swelling in the left lower eyelid for the last two months. Palpation of the mass indicates a small nodule in the substance of the eyelid not involving the lid margin. The overlying skin is normal and mobile and eversion of the eyelid shows a mass in the tarsal plate. The girl is a known patient of blepharitis. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Basal cell carcinoma",
      "Chalazion",
      "Hordeolum Externum (Stye)",
      "Hordeolum Internum",
      "Squamous cell carcinoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Chalazion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 45 years old female who was on chemotherapeutics for her breast cancer presented with facial pain from the last 10 days. O/E extensive black eschars and crustings were noted in both sides of nasal cavity. She underwent FESS and aggressive surgical debridement. Post op she was put on amphotericin to control the spread of her nasal pathology. Which of the following parameters will need strict monitoring:",
    "options": [
      "Blood sugar levels",
      "Cardiac enzymes",
      "Electrolytes",
      "Prothrombin Time",
      "Renal profile"
    ],
    "answer": "Renal profile"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 37 years female patient presented to eye opd with pain and photophobia. On Slit lamp examination she is having corneal ulcer with feathery edges. Following is the most helpful investigation?",
    "options": [
      "Bacterial culture",
      "Viral profile",
      "Methamine silver",
      "Culture media enriched with E-col",
      "Interferon Gamma releasing assay"
    ],
    "answer": "Methamine silver"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2-year boy is brought to the outpatient department with right upper eyelid droop since birth. Examination reveals an absent right upper lid crease and 5 mm of ptosis. Which surgical procedure is the most appropriate?",
    "options": [
      "Frontalis Sling",
      "Levator resection",
      "Fasanella Servat procedure",
      "Observation",
      "Aponeurotic strengthening"
    ],
    "answer": "Frontalis Sling"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35 years old male with nasal polyposis and seasonal allergic rhinitis is evaluated in clinic. Upon enquiry, he is found to be allergic to aspirin too. You are suspecting that this patient has samter’s triad. What other pathology would you expect in this patient as a part of this triad:",
    "options": [
      "Anosmia",
      "Bronchial asthma",
      "dextrocardia",
      "Infertility",
      "sensorineural hearing loss"
    ],
    "answer": "Bronchial asthma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 13 months old child is brought by the mother to eye opd with the complaint of low vision of the child. The ophthalmologist while doing the ocular examination notices that the pupil reflex is white in the right eye. What will be the most important differential diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Congential glaucoma",
      "Corneal scar",
      "Corneal ulcer",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Refractive error"
    ],
    "answer": "Retinoblastoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20-year-old presents to the emergency department with fever and left eye proptosis for 3 days. On examination, he has restricted ocular movements and decreased vision. He is diagnosed with orbital cellulitis. Considering the most common source of infection spreading to the orbit, what is the most likely origin?",
    "options": [
      "Dacryocystitis",
      "Dental infection",
      "Endogenous (hematogenous) spread",
      "Paranasal sinuses (sinusitis)",
      "Acute hordeolum"
    ],
    "answer": "Paranasal sinuses (sinusitis)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 days baby is brought by his parents for evaluation of watering from eyes. On examination, the patient has excessive lacrimation. He has cloudy corneas with Haab’s striae. His corneal diameters are 13 mm. His intra-ocular pressure is 28 mm of Hg in both eyes. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Congenital Naso-lacrimal duct obstruction",
      "Congenital glaucoma",
      "Congenital cataract",
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Bacterial corneal ulcer"
    ],
    "answer": "Congenital glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 years old male patient came to Ophthalmology outpatient department with complaints of decreased vision in his right eye since last 1 year. The decreased vision is painless, gradual and not associated with any trauma. The visual acuity in right eye is counting fingers close to the eye. On examination he has white pupillary reflex. Rest of the clinical examination is normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Retinoblastoma",
      "Relative afferent pupillary defect",
      "Age related cataract",
      "Coat’s disease",
      "Age related macular degeneration"
    ],
    "answer": "Age related cataract"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 42 yr old man presents to eye OPD with complaint of transient obscuration of vision in both eyes lasting 10-15 seconds many times a day. He also has a headache which is more severe early in the morning and is aggravated by coughing, sneezing and straining. He also reports sudden episodes of nausea and vomiting. Visual acuity and pupils are normal. On fundoscopy optic discs are hyperemic, elevated with blurred margins and engorged veins at the disc margins with absent venous pulsation. MRI brain shows a tumor in the posterior cranial fossa. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Papilloedema",
      "Anterior ischemic optic neuropathy",
      "Pseudopapilloedema",
      "optic neuritis"
    ],
    "answer": "Papilloedema"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 25-year-old male came to ENT OPD with complaint of persistent purulent right ear discharge from the last 15 years but lately he noticed hearing loss in same ear. His hearing becomes better when he got discharge but become worse when he get antibiotic for it and discharge becomes dry. What is the most common cause of hearing loss in this patient",
    "options": [
      "adhesions of middle ear",
      "Tympanic membrane perforation",
      "cochlear damage due to toxic absorption",
      "Edema of the ear canal due to infection"
    ],
    "answer": "Tympanic membrane perforation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50 years old male patient came through opd with the history of hard-of-hearing and foul smelling left ear discharge for the last 6-7 years. The patient developed headache and nausea for the last 7-10 days. The patient fails to take the names of common objects like cup and saucer but can demonstrate their use. What would be the possible cause of this condition;",
    "options": [
      "Chronic otitis media with cholesteatoma",
      "cerebellar brain abscess",
      "Lateral sinus thrombosis",
      "Otitic hydrocephalus",
      "Temporal lobe abscess"
    ],
    "answer": "Temporal lobe abscess"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 3 weeks old infant is brought by his mother to eye OPD after noticing a white dot in his left eye. After complete eye examination and investigation a diagnosis of dense unilateral cataract is made in his left eye without any ocular or systemic association. His right eye is completely normal. Which of the following is the treatment of choice for this infant?",
    "options": [
      "Glasses",
      "Contact lens",
      "Observation",
      "Cataract surgery",
      "Laser photocoagulation"
    ],
    "answer": "Cataract surgery"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 10 years old male is brought to emergency with complaints of high grade fever and difficulty breathing from the last 2 days. He had an episode of upper respiratory tract infection 7 days back. O/E, patient is dyspneic with inspiratory stridor. X ray neck lateral view shows an enlarged prevertebral soft tissue shadow indicating retropharyngeal abscess. The next step would be:",
    "options": [
      "IV antibiotics",
      "hydration",
      "antibiotics",
      "tracheostomy"
    ],
    "answer": "tracheostomy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20 year man presents to eye OPD with the complaint of appearance of a fleshy mass after trauma to the left eye for the last 05 months. On examination of the left eye the bulbar conjunctival fold is adherent to the cornea at 6 o clock Position. A probe can be passed under the neck of the probe. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Pterygium",
      "Psudopterygium",
      "Pingicula",
      "scleritis",
      "episcleritis"
    ],
    "answer": "Psudopterygium"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 6 years old female presented with complaints of left sided nasal obstruction and foul smelling nasal discharge from the last 1 year. Her parents denied any history of fever. X ray PNS revealed a radio opaque lucency in left side nasal cavity. The diagnosis in this case would be",
    "options": [
      "enlarged adenoids",
      "foreign body nose",
      "nasal polyposis",
      "seasonal allergic rhinitis"
    ],
    "answer": "foreign body nose"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old male presented with complaints of right sided tinnitus and vertigo from the last 5 years. he has taken multiple medications for it but with no improvement. Rather his symptoms have worsened over time. O/E right TM is normal. Tuning fork tests are also normal. The next investigation in this patient would be",
    "options": [
      "Audiogram",
      "brain stem evoked response audiometry",
      "electrocochleography",
      "MRI brain",
      "speech discrimination score"
    ],
    "answer": "MRI brain"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70 yrs old lady comes to eye OPD with the complaint of gradual dimness of vision in both eyes. On examination the visual acuity in both eyes is counting fingers 1 meter. The most common cause of visual impairment according to WHO estimation is ?",
    "options": [
      "Glaucoma",
      "Age related macular degeneration",
      "cataract",
      "Diabetic retinopathy",
      "Corneal opacification"
    ],
    "answer": "cataract"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70 years old lady presented to EYE-OPD with the complaints of watering and foreign body sensation. On examination she has scarring of the upper palpebral conjunctiva, Herbert pits at the superior limbus and superior pannus. The type of entropion the patient is suffering from is:",
    "options": [
      "Acute spastic Entropion",
      "Cicatricial Entropion",
      "Congenital Entropion",
      "Epiblepharon",
      "Involutional Entropion"
    ],
    "answer": "Cicatricial Entropion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Drooping of upper eyelid & absence of eyelid crease since birth occurs in:",
    "options": [
      "Congenital entropion",
      "Simple congenital ptosis",
      "Homer syndrome",
      "Congenital 3rd nerve palsy",
      "Congenital ectropion"
    ],
    "answer": "Simple congenital ptosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 15 years old female presented with right post auricular swelling from the last 5 days. She has a history of chronic discharge from right ear for the last 4 years. O/E patient is febrile with right ear discharge and tender swelling in the right post auricular area which is fluctuant. The next step should be:",
    "options": [
      "Broad spectrum antibiotics",
      "conservative management",
      "incision and drainage of abscess",
      "examination under a microscope",
      "right mastoid exploration"
    ],
    "answer": "incision and drainage of abscess"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 33-year-old lady is brought to ophthalmology emergency after she suffered trauma to her right eye with scissors. Her visual acuity is counting fingers close to the eye. On examination, she has corneal edema, and corneal perforation at 5 o'clock with iris prolapse. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Closed globe injury",
      "open globe injury",
      "iris melanoma",
      "Corneal ulcer",
      "Traumatic cataract"
    ],
    "answer": "open globe injury"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 6-month-old boy is brought by his parents to ophthalmology OPD for watering from both eyes. The patient has bilateral enlarged corneas and the corneas look hazy on clinical examination. His intraocular pressure is noted to be 30mm of Hg in both eyes. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Bacterial keratitis",
      "Congenital Nasolacrimal duct obstruction",
      "Bacterial conjunctivitis",
      "Anterior Uveitis",
      "Congenital Glaucoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Congenital Glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mother has brought her 8 years old son to eye OPD for concerns of redness of eyes and itching. According to the mother, her son frequently rubs his eyes and is unable to go out in the sun due to photophobia. The condition is there since last 4 years. It is typically worse in spring and summers. On examination the patient has cobble-stone papillae on his tarsal conjunctiva. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Bacterial Conjunctivitis",
      "Vernal Kerato-conjunctivitis",
      "Congenital Naso-lacrimal duct obstruction",
      "Viral Conjunctivitis",
      "Corneal Ulcer"
    ],
    "answer": "Vernal Kerato-conjunctivitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A father brings his 2 years old child with a complaint of whitish pupillary reflex and squint in the child's right eye. Eye examination reveals a large whitish retinal mass involving more than half of the retina and protruding into the vitreous cavity. A clinical diagnosis of retinoblastoma is made. MRI reveals a 2mm extension of the tumor along the optic nerve. Which of the following is the best treatment modality indicated for this child?",
    "options": [
      "chemotherapy",
      "brachytherapy",
      "External beam radiotherapy",
      "Laser photocoagulation",
      "Enucleation"
    ],
    "answer": "Enucleation"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 17-year-old patient visits your clinic with complaints of a persistent sore throat, mild fever and discomfort in the abdomen. Physical examination reveals swollen tonsils with scrapable white patches and palpable cervical lymph nodes. The patient's fatigue seems disproportionate to the symptoms. What condition should be considered in this case?",
    "options": [
      "common cold",
      "Gastroenteritis",
      "diphtheria",
      "streptococcal tonsitis"
    ],
    "answer": "streptococcal tonsitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old male who is a wood worker by profession presented with complaints of right side blood stained nasal discharge and right sided peri orbital pain from the last 3 months. On nasal endoscopy, patient had an ulcerated and fungating growth arising from the right anterior ethmoids. Histopathology of tumor this patient will likely reveal:",
    "options": [
      "Mucoepidermoid carcinoma",
      "nasopharyngeal carcinoma",
      "squamous cell carcinoma",
      "Undifferentiated carcinoma"
    ],
    "answer": "squamous cell carcinoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35 yrs old lady who is a known patient of multiple sclerosis presents to eye emergency department with complaint of acute visual loss in her left eye. She reports pain on extraocular movements. Her visual acuity in the left eye is 6/60 and color vision is markedly impaired. Pupillary examination shows relative afferent pupillary defect. Fundoscopy shows a swollen and hyperemic optic disc with blurred margins. Macula is normal. Vitreous contains inflammatory cells. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Papilledema",
      "Anterior ischemic optic neuropathy",
      "Pseudopapilledema",
      "Optic neuritis",
      "Neuroretinitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Optic neuritis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 13 years old boy with angiofibroma is due to undergo surgery. However there are concerns regarding per operative blood loss owing to the highly vascular nature of the tumor. Which of the following would you request to reduce per operative blood loss in this patient:",
    "options": [
      "cell salvage devices",
      "external carotid artery ligation",
      "embolization",
      "hormonal therapy",
      "transfuse whole blood pre op"
    ],
    "answer": "embolization"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 32 year old farmer presents to eye OPD with complaints of blurring of vision right eye and watering. he had a history of left eye trauma with a sickle 3 weeks ago resulting in iris prolapse for which he underwent primary repair surgery. on examination of right eye the eye is red, there is anterior uveitis. on fundoscopy he has multifocal choroidal infiltrates in mid periphery. what is your most likely diagnosis",
    "options": [
      "endophthalmitis",
      "uveitis",
      "chalcosis",
      "siderosis bulbi",
      "sympathetic ophthalmia"
    ],
    "answer": "sympathetic ophthalmia"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old diabetic female presented to opd with complaints of left sided facial swelling pain from the last 7 days. According to her, the pain aggravates while eating food. O/E, left parotid is diffusely enlarged with overlying erythema, however facial nerve is intact. The next step in management of this patient would be:",
    "options": [
      "IV antibiotics",
      "incision and drainage",
      "obtain an ultrasound",
      "superficial parotidectomy"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain an ultrasound"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 50 years old diabetic male with end stage renal disease received a renal transplant. 1 month after surgery, he presented with facial pain, decreased vision right eye and swelling of the right orbit. O/E he had extensive black eschars and crusting right side nasal cavity. The right eye had complete ophthalmoplegia with paralysis of all muscles, no pupillary reflexes and no vision. The mechanism which would explain the findings in right eye would be:",
    "options": [
      "Cavernous sinus thrombosis",
      "direct invasion of orbit",
      "involvement of optic nerve",
      "Loss of corneal reflex",
      "Relative afferent pupillary defect"
    ],
    "answer": "Cavernous sinus thrombosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 4 years old male presented with complaints of nasal obstruction and snoring from the last 2 years. He was investigated and found to have enlarged adenoids. He underwent adenoidectomy which was uneventful and then discharged home. He presented again after a week with complaints of nasal regurge of food and nasal speech. The next step would be",
    "options": [
      "Intravenous antibiotics",
      "Pass an NG for feeding",
      "palatal reconstruction",
      "Perform a tonsillectomy",
      "Re assure and manage conservatively"
    ],
    "answer": "Re assure and manage conservatively"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 years old female patient presents to eye OPD with history of decreased vision and mild pain in her right eye since last 5 months. She is a known case of rheumatoid arthritis. On examination she has mutton fat keratic precipitates on the cornea, mild anterior chamber reaction iris nodules and posterior synechiae. What is the most likely diagnosis:",
    "options": [
      "acute anterior uveitis",
      "chronic anterior Uveitis",
      "fuchs heterochromic Uveitis",
      "sympathetic opthalmia",
      "endophthalmitis"
    ],
    "answer": "chronic anterior Uveitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 55 yrs old lady comes to eye OPD with the complaint of gradual dimness of vision in both eyes. Intraocular pressure in both eyes is 30mmHg. Anterior segments are normal. Fundi show advanced optic disc cupping. Visual fields show double arcuate and temporal wedge scotomas. The diagnosis of the lady is",
    "options": [
      "cataract",
      "age related macular degeneration",
      "diabetic retinopathy",
      "glaucoma",
      "hypertensive retinopathy"
    ],
    "answer": "glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 15 years old boy present to Eye-OPD with a history of a sudden appearance of a painful mass at right upper lid margin for the last one day. It contains pus at the peak of the mass. The skin around the mass is red and oedematous. He also have some refractive error and gives history of the appearance of such a mass in the past. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Basal cell carcinoma",
      "chalazion",
      "Hordeolum Externum (Stye)",
      "Hordeolum Internum",
      "squamous cell carcinoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Hordeolum Externum (Stye)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35 years old female presented with loosening of left upper molars and left facial pain from the last 1 year. O/E her 2nd last left upper molar has fallen off with loosening of the rest. Nasal examination revealed a fungating growth arising from left maxillary sinus with blood stained discharge. you are suspecting sinonasal malignancy. Which investigation would you order to assess spread of the disease:",
    "options": [
      "Angiography",
      "CT scan",
      "Nasal endoscopy",
      "Xray PNS"
    ],
    "answer": "CT scan"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 31 years old male patient come to ENT clinic with the history of bilateral nasal obstruction for the last 10 months. associated with post nasal drips and hyposmia. Examination reveals bilateral nasal polyposis. CT nose and paranasal sinuses shows differential densities in maxillary sinuses and ethmoid sinuses. Peroperative caseous and jelly like materials found along with nasal polyps. What is the most probable diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Acute bacterial rhinosinusitis",
      "Antrochoanal polyps",
      "Bilateral ethmoidal polyposis",
      "Mucormycosis"
    ],
    "answer": "Bilateral ethmoidal polyposis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 55-year man presents with unilateral facial weakness due to facial nerve (7th cranial nerve) palsy. On examination, he has difficulty closing his affected eye completely, and the lower eyelid is turned outward, resulting in ectropion. What is the underlying mechanism responsible for the ectropion in this patient?",
    "options": [
      "Increased tone of orbicularis oculi muscle",
      "Paralysis of orbicularis oculi muscle",
      "Underactivity of levator palpebrae superioris muscle",
      "Contracture of the tarsal plate causing ectropion",
      "Hypersecretion of lacrimal gland causing eyelid edema and ectropion"
    ],
    "answer": "Paralysis of orbicularis oculi muscle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pinna of the human ear is a corrugated structure that is the integral part of hearing system. You think the most significant feature of Pinna is;",
    "options": [
      "Frost bite s more common on medial aspects of the pinna",
      "Hearing",
      "Incisura terminalis for Wilde's incision",
      "Looking normal",
      "Tragal cartilage can be used in rhinoplasty"
    ],
    "answer": "Hearing"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 year old male patient came to ENT opd with complain of decrease hearing and ear discharge from both ears for the last 5 years. On otoscopic examination there is a central perforation of both tympanic membranes. Normal cochlear function on audiogram with 30 db HL for bone conduction. The most likely hearing loss in this patient would be",
    "options": [
      "sensorineural deafness",
      "mixed HL",
      "conductive deafness",
      "Malingering",
      "Normal hearing"
    ],
    "answer": "conductive deafness"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 53 years old male healthy patient came through OPD with the history of nasal obstruction, headache associated with sneezing, watery eyes and post nasal drip. On examination he has periorbital edema and nasal polyposis. The nasal discharge has eosinophilia and Charcot -Leyden crystals. Which of the following describes best the aforementioned conditions;",
    "options": [
      "Acute rhinosinusitis",
      "Allergic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyposis",
      "Allergic fungal rhinosinusitis",
      "Chronic rhinosinusitis",
      "Chronic invasive fungal rhinosinusitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Allergic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyposis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 35 years old male athlete was involved in contact sport. During his recent rugby match, he received a sharp blow to his right temporal bone. He was rushed off the field and to the emergency department. O/E, patient had developed a right facial paralysis, but rest of examination was normal. The attending surgeon planned him for facial nerve decompression. which segment of facial nerve carries a high risk of involvement in this case and should be decompressed immediately",
    "options": [
      "Intracranial segment",
      "Labyrinthine segment",
      "Meatal segment",
      "Tympani segment",
      "Vertical segment"
    ],
    "answer": "Labyrinthine segment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 65 years old man present to EYE-OPD with irritation and foreign body sensation in the left eye for the last one month. On examination the left lower eyelid margin is turned towards the eyeball. The overlying skin is normal. On eversion of the eyelid the lid margin comes to its normal position but inverts again on forceful closure of the eyelid. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Acute spastic Entropion",
      "Cicatricial Entropion",
      "Congenital Entropion",
      "Epiblepharon",
      "Involutional Entropion"
    ],
    "answer": "Involutional Entropion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old lady comes to eye opd with a complaint of localized redness and mild discomfort. on examination the patient has a mobile, reddish nodule beneath the conjunctiva. on installation of a single drop of phenylephrine 2.5%, the dilated vessels blench and the redness reduces. the most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "necrotizing scleritis without inflammation",
      "nodular episcleritis",
      "posterior scleritis",
      "Viral conjunctivitis",
      "bacterial conjunctivitis"
    ],
    "answer": "nodular episcleritis"
  },
  {
    "question": "An 80 years old female presents to eye OPD with the complaints of persistent right epiphora. On examination the right lower eyelid is everted away from the eyeball. She has right chronic conjunctivitis and exposure keratitis. the most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "trichiases",
      "ectropion",
      "entropion",
      "districhiases",
      "psudo districhiases"
    ],
    "answer": "ectropion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 32-year-old woman presents to the ENT outpatient clinic with sudden onset of severe vertigo, nausea, and vomiting for the past 2 days. She reports that the vertigo began after an episode of upper respiratory tract infection one week ago. She also complains of decreased hearing and tinnitus in the left ear. There is no history of head trauma or use of ototoxic drugs. On examination, she has spontaneous horizontal nystagmus beating to the right and a positive Romberg’s test falling to the left side. The tympanic membranes appear normal.",
    "options": [
      "Vestibular neuritis",
      "Benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV)",
      "Labyrinthitis",
      "Meniere's disease",
      "Acoustic neuroma"
    ],
    "answer": "Labyrinthitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 26 years old male patient presents to Ophthalmology outpatient department with complaints of sudden onset of painless decreased vision since last 2 days. It is associated with floaters and flashes of light. He is a known high myope. He observed the decreased vision as a curtain falling from above. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Optic neuritis",
      "Retinal detachment",
      "Age related cataract",
      "Keratoconus",
      "Hyphaema"
    ],
    "answer": "Retinal detachment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 34 years old female patient came through OPD with the history of nasal obstruction, mucopurulent nasal discharge associated with headache and facial pain worsens with straining and bending over. What do you think it would be",
    "options": [
      "Acute rhinosinusitis",
      "Allergic rhinosinusitis",
      "Acute invasive fungal rhinosinusitis",
      "Chronic rhinosinusitis",
      "Chronic invasive fungal rhinosinusitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Acute rhinosinusitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 64 year old man who is diabetic presents with severe otalgia with otorrhea. Examination shows granulation tissue in the floor of ear canal and a swab culture comes back as pseudomonas aeruginosa. The likely diagnosis in the case will be",
    "options": [
      "Otomycosis",
      "Neoplastic process",
      "Epidermal cyst",
      "Malignant necrotizing otitis externa",
      "Exostosis of the ear canal"
    ],
    "answer": "Malignant necrotizing otitis externa"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 7 year old child was brought to the ENT clinic with acute right sided ear pain for the last 2 days. He was having an acute upper respiratory infection for seven days. Examination of tympanic membrane shows radial vascular markings on bulging tympanic membrane. He was given 10 days antibiotic course but didn't complete it due to non-compliance. After 10 days he had no fever but still complaining of hearing loss. The most common cause of hearing loss is",
    "options": [
      "acute suppurative otitis media",
      "Secretory otitis media",
      "Chronic suppurative otitis media",
      "cochlear damage due to toxic absorption of pus in middle ear",
      "otosclerosis"
    ],
    "answer": "Secretory otitis media"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 22-year-old male patient is a known high myope since last 15 years. He has recently discovered sudden onset of decrease vision In his left eye. The decrease vision was painless and associated with flashes and floaters of light. He had noticed it as a 'curtain falling down’ on his left eye. What is the most likely diagnosis in this patient?",
    "options": [
      "cataract",
      "Open angle glaucoma",
      "Viral Keratitis",
      "Retinal detachment",
      "Hyphaema"
    ],
    "answer": "Retinal detachment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 25 years old male presented with complaints of runny nose, sneezing and itching from the last 5 years. According to him, his symptoms get worse every spring during the pollen season. O/E, he has pale looking nasal mucosa and whitish nasal discharge. The patient is suffering from",
    "options": [
      "chronic rhinosinusitis",
      "fungal rhinosinusitis",
      "rhinitis sicca",
      "seasonal allergic rhinitis",
      "vasomotor rhinitis"
    ],
    "answer": "seasonal allergic rhinitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 yrs old man who is a known patient of Glaucoma comes to eye OPD with the request of checking his intraocular pressures (IOP). The Ophthalmologist puts anesthetic eye drops over the cornea of the patient and checked the IOP. The instrument which is used for checking IOP is called:",
    "options": [
      "slit lamp biomicroscope",
      "Tonometer",
      "ophthalmoscope",
      "Retinoscope",
      "Pachymeter"
    ],
    "answer": "Tonometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 yrs old lady with a pregnancy of 8 months who has developed hypertension, proteinuria and generalized body edema is complaining of sudden onset dimness of vision in both eyes. On fundoscopy there is generalized narrowing of arterioles, cotton wool spots and superficial retinal haemorrhages. In addition there is retinal edema and hard exudates. The patient is suffering from :",
    "options": [
      "Hypertensive retinopathy",
      "Central retinal artery occlusion",
      "Diabetic retinopathy",
      "Toxemia of pregnancy"
    ],
    "answer": "Toxemia of pregnancy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 55 years old female presented with the complaints of bilateral tinnitus and hearing loss from the last 8 years. she complained of occasional vertigo along with it. On further investigating the patient, she was found to have bilateral acoustic neuromas. The attending surgeon wanted to screen her for a gene mutation. The genetic analysis should include:",
    "options": [
      "cystic fibrosis gene",
      "MEN 1 gene",
      "Neurofibromatosis 2 gene",
      "RET proto oncogene",
      "p53 gene"
    ],
    "answer": "Neurofibromatosis 2 gene"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 70-year man presents to the ophthalmology outpatient department with a painless, shiny, firm, indurated nodule on his lower eyelid. The lesion has visible blood vessels on its surface. He is suspected to have basal cell carcinoma. Which type of basal cell carcinoma is most consistent with the gross examination findings?",
    "options": [
      "Noduloulcerative",
      "Sclerosing or Morpheaform",
      "Nodular",
      "Keratoacanthoma",
      "Pyogenic granuloma"
    ],
    "answer": "Nodular"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 58 yr old lady having cataracts in both eyes presents to eye emergency department with the complaint of sudden onset of pain and gross dimness of vision in her right eye. On examination of the right eye the cornea is edematous, anterior chamber is shallow, pupil is mid-dilated, with dense cataract, intraocular pressure is 60mmHg. The lady is suffering from:",
    "options": [
      "Pigmentary glaucoma",
      "Inflammatory glaucoma",
      "Neovascular glaucoma",
      "Phacomorphic glaucoma",
      "Pseudoexfoliation glaucoma"
    ],
    "answer": "Phacomorphic glaucoma"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 9-year-old boy presents with persistent ear discharge, fever, and pain behind the right ear for 5 days. He had acute otitis media two weeks ago that improved intially with antibiotics but then worsened. On examination, his right postauricular area is swollen, red, and tender with loss of the postauricular sulcus and downward-forward displacement of the pinna. Otoscopy reveals a bulging posterior canal wall and purulent discharge through a central tympanic membrane perforation.",
    "options": [
      "Acute otitis externa",
      "Cholesteatoma",
      "Acute mastoiditis",
      "serous otitis media",
      "otitis media with effusion"
    ],
    "answer": "Acute mastoiditis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 25 years old male patient came from Afghanistan with the history of hard-of-hearing and painless foul smelling ear discharge for the last 6-7 months. On otoscopy the tympanic membrane has multiple small perforations and pale granulations in the middle ear cavity. What do you expect of the following?",
    "options": [
      "Aero-otitis media",
      "chronic otitis media",
      "Recurrent acute otitis media",
      "syphilitic otitis media",
      "Tubercular otitis media"
    ],
    "answer": "Tubercular otitis media"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20 years old female presented with sudden onset vertigo from the last 4 hours. She also has nausea and vomiting along with it. She reports having a viral flu 4 days back. O/E both tympanic membranes are intact and normal. Tuning fork tests are also normal. The pathology in this patient is",
    "options": [
      "Acoustic neuroma",
      "Benign paroxysmal positional vertigo",
      "Meniere's disease",
      "Labyrinthitis",
      "Vestibular neuronitis"
    ],
    "answer": "Vestibular neuronitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 years old lady presents to eye OPD with the complaint of a sudden onset appearance of redness in the outer part of right eye. She is also complaining of hotness, pricking sensation and discomfort in right eye. On examination of the right eye straight inflamed vessels are radiating posteriorly from the limbus and the lesion moves with cotton tipped applicator over the deeper tissue. The most probable diagnosis is:",
    "options": [
      "Pterygium",
      "Pseudopteryglum",
      "Pingicula",
      "Scleritis",
      "Episcleritis"
    ],
    "answer": "Episcleritis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 30 year old copper smith presented to eye OPD with decreased vision left eye He had history of trauma to left eye while working 2 months back. on examination his VA is 6/60, cornea of left eye has Kayser Fleischer ring. he also has left developing sunflower cataract. examination of the retina shows golden yellow plaques, he most likely has",
    "options": [
      "siderosis bulbi",
      "uveitis",
      "endophthalmitis",
      "sympathetic ophthalmia"
    ],
    "answer": "siderosis bulbi"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 45 years male presented to eye OPD with a complaint of right inward deviation in primary position and sudden diplopia. Extra ocular movements are normal except right lateral rectus restriction. Diplopia increases on ipsilateral gaze. What's the probable diagnosis:",
    "options": [
      "3rd nerve palsy",
      "6th nerve palsy",
      "duane retraction syndrome",
      "convergence spasm",
      "Restrictive thyroid ophthalmopathy"
    ],
    "answer": "6th nerve palsy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2 years male old child presented with complaints of bilaterally decreased hearing since birth. Her parents report that he had neonatal jaundice at 10th day of life for which he required an exchange transfusion for his high bilirubin levels. Audiogram reveals he has 100dB of sensorineural hearing loss bilaterally. The option he has for auditory rehabilitation is",
    "options": [
      "brain stem implant",
      "cochlear implant",
      "hearing aid",
      "non verbal cues",
      "wait and watch policy"
    ],
    "answer": "cochlear implant"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 40 years old patient presents to eye OPD with complaints of sudden onset of painful swelling near the medial canthus area. The swelling is tender to touch and red. The patient had previously watering from the eye. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "chronic Dacrocystitis",
      "Acute on chronic dacrocystitis",
      "Lacrimal gland tumor",
      "stye",
      "chalazion"
    ],
    "answer": "Acute on chronic dacrocystitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 24 years old female presented with complaints of chronically discharging ears from the last 4 years. She has taken multiple antibiotics with no improvement. Examination of the ears reveal bilateral perforations with active discharge In both ears. Her CT scan shows hazy mastoids. The next investigation in this patient which will help in management is:",
    "options": [
      "audiogram",
      "Examination under a microscope",
      "full blood profile",
      "Pus for culture and sensitivity",
      "MRI brain"
    ],
    "answer": "Pus for culture and sensitivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 60 yrs old hypertensive man presents to eye emergency with sudden onset painless loss of the right eye. Visual acuity is 6/60 in the right and 6/6 in the left eye. On fundoscopy spontaneous venous pulsation over the optic disc is absent. Retinal veins are dilated, engorged and tortuous. Haemorrhages are present in all four quadrants, along the veins. Optic disc and macula are edematous. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "Central retinal vein occlusion",
      "Hypertensive retinopathy",
      "Central retinal artery occlusion",
      "Diabetic retinopathy",
      "Toxemia of pregnancy"
    ],
    "answer": "Central retinal vein occlusion"
  }
]